A Guide to the Rockefeller Archive Center Oral History and Audio Recordings Collection FA1444
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Archive Center Oral History and Audio Recordings Collection
1949-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
Jackson Hole Preserve, Incorporated
FA1444
1.9 Cubic Feet 36 audio recordings, and 5 letter document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains audio recordings of oral histories and interviews, as well as documentation of the interviews, and associated supplementary material.
Types of documentation and supplementary material include:
Transcript: A verbatim script of the interview.
Catalogue: A point by point list of topics covered in the interview.
Account: A narrative, non-verbatim write up of the interview.
Notes: Supplementary material which can include biographical and background information on the interviewee, a list of questions used in the interview, correspondence regarding the interview, drafts of the transcript, and a release form signed by the interviewee.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series as follows:
Series 1: Oral History Collection Audio
Series 2: Additional Rockefeller Family Audio Recordings
Series 3: Interviews and Oral History - Paper Files
Series 4: Interviews and Oral History - Microfiche
Series 5: Jackson Hole Preserve Project
Series 6: Nelson A. Rockefeller Project
Sound recordings
- Oral History Collection Audio, 1957-1989 (bulk 1970s); 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphebetically by subject.
  Scope and Contents
  Interviews with Rockefeller family members and associates.
  - Bartlett, Jane - Part 1, 1973 October 16; Sound, 114 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9912)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy available.
    Personal secretary to Winthrop Rockefeller. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Little Rock, Arkansas.
  - Bartlett, Jane - Part 2, 1973 October 16; Sound, 69 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9913)
  - Black, Margaret, 1973 October 18; Sound, 115 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9914)
    Housekeeper at Winrock Farm. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Winrock Farm, Arkansas.
  - Claude, Dr. Albert, 1976 July 19; 1976 July 26; Sound, 259 minutes; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 9928)
    Cellular biologist at Rockefeller University, 1929-1949. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Pocantico Hills, NY.
  - Decker, Norma, 1970 April 22; Sound, 46 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9899)
  - Douglas, Howard, 1971 December 9; Sound, 37 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9903)
    Messenger and receptionist at the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller, 1925-1971.
  - Ernst, Joseph, 1981 June 27; Sound, 60 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9925)
    Rockefeller family archivist, 1953-1987. Director, Rockefeller Archive Center, 1975-1987. Interviewed at Pocantico Hills, NY.
  - Hudson, James - Part 1, 1973 May 1; Sound, 57 minutes; 1/4 inch audio reel (Box 2, Reel AV 9910)
    Associate of Winthrop Rockefeller. Interviewed by Linda Edgerly, New York, NY.
  - Hudson, James - Part 2, 1973 May 1; Sound, 50 minutes; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 9911)
  - King, Charles S., 1974 September 25; Sound, 30 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9906)
    Office assistant at the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller, 1931-1972. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst.
  - King, Charles S. - Part 1, 1972 April 10; Sound, 61 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9904)
  - King, Charles S. - Part 2, 1972 April 10; Sound, 19 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9905)
  - Mambert, Helen - Part 1, 1970 April 6; Sound, 50 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9900)
    Resident of Richford. Interviewed by John Camp.
  - Mambert, Helen - Part 2, 1970 April 8; Sound, 45 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9901)
  - McLeod, Mary, 1973 October 15; Sound, 103 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9915)
    Assistant to Winthrop Rockefeller. Executive Vice President and Treasurer of the Rockwin Fund. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Little Rock, Arkansas.
  - Chasin, Laura Rockefeller -- Reading Her Notes from Abby "Babs" Rockefeller Mauze Interview, 1973 November 10; Sound, 40 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9916)
    New York, New York. Laura Rockefeller Chasin reading, at length, her notes from a conversation she conducted with her aunt Abby "Babs" Rockefeller Mauze. The recording may have been made for transcription purposes. Abby "Babs" Rockefeller Mauze is not on the recording.
  - Rockefeller, David, 1973 December 7; Sound, 19 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9926)
    Philanthropist, banker, son of John D. Rockefeller, Jr and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. Interviewed by Richard Salomon, William Wing, Warren Lindquist, and Joseph W. Ernst, Hudson Pines.
  - Rockefeller, David, 1975 July 22; Sound, 111 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2, Tape AV 9927)
  - Rockefeller, Jeannette - Part 1, 1974 April 22; Sound, 60 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9918)
    Wife of Winthrop Rockefeller. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, New York, New York.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Recording is silent for a few minutes approximately one-third of the way into interview.
  - Rockefeller, Jeannette - Part 2, 1974 April 22; Sound, 29 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9919)
  - Rockefeller, Laurance S., 1977 December; Sound, 55 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9922)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller discussing Dr. George Cotzias. LSR spoke at his memorial service on December 14, 1977. Interviewed by George D. Taylor, [December 7, 1977?].
  - Rockefeller, Mary French, 1972 December 7; Sound, 18 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9907)
    Wife of Laurance S. Rockefeller. Speech by her upon receipt of National Institute of Social Sciences Award.
  - Stremlau, John - Part 1, 1989 January 12; Sound, 28 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2, Tape AV 9931)
    Director of the Rockefeller Foundation's International Relations Program, associate of David Rockefeller. Interviewed by Emily J. Oakhill, RAC Archivist, Pocantico Hills, New York.
  - Stremlau, John - Part 1 and 2, 1989 January 12; 1989 January 20; Sound, 80 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2, Tape AV 9933)
  - Stremlau, John - Part 2, 1989 January 20; Sound, 24 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2, Tape AV 9932)
  - Tour of Pocantico Hills with Vincent Frasca and Bob Snyder, 1974 December 3; Sound, 50 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9920)
  - (1) - Turk, Mr and Mrs. Clyde (2) - Rockefeller, Ray, (1) 1970 April 8. (2) 1970 April 7; Sound, 93 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9902)
    Richford residents. Interviewed by John Camp.
  - Willets, Edmund R., Undated; Sound, 13 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2, Tape AV 9930)
    Standard Oil Company representative, Accompanied John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to China in 1921. Anecdotes of trip to China as related by Col. William L. Howard.
  - Winger, Richard, 1957; Sound, 39 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9921)
    Josephine Fabian informal interview of Dick and Marta Winger, winter 1957.
  - Winger, Richard, 1957; Sound, 39 minutes; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2, Reel AV 9923)
    Josephine Fabian informal interview of Dick and Marta Winger, winter 1957. Same interview as in AV 9921 and AV 9924.
  - Winger, Richard, 1957; Sound, 38 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9924)
    Josephine Fabian interview of Dick and Marta Winger, winter 1957. Same interview as in AV 9921 and AV 9923.
  - Wirth, Conrad - Part 1, 1989 May 1; Sound, 92 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2, Tape AV 9934)
    Director of the National Park Service. Associate of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Wirth, Conrad - Part 1, 1989 May 1; Sound, 91 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2, Tape AV 9935)
- Additional Rockefeller Family Audio Recordings, 1974; 2
  - What's Happening - Channel 3 - Hartford, Connecticut: Topic: "The National Caucus of Labor Committees", 1974 April 20; Sound, 42 minutes; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 9917)
    Popular music, random television sound, and silence for first 13 minutes. Recording with various members and ex-members from the The National Caucus of Labor Committees (NCLC) and other political opponents stating their disatisfaction with the Rockefellers.
    Appears to be multiple programs.
    Audio pitched high.
- Interviews and Oral History - Paper Files, 3
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bartlette, Jane - Catalogue, Notes, 1973 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
    Withrop Rockefeller's personal secretary, interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Little Rock Arkansas
  - Baverstock, Mr. and Mrs. William - Account, 1968 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Pocantico Hills Residents, 1917-1941. Interviewed 1968 April 8
  - Black, Margaret - Catalogue, Notes, 1973 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Housekeeper at Winrock Farm. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Winrock Farm, Arkansas
  - Champman, Mr. and Mrs. Howard, 1973 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Members of the Stongsville (Ohio) Historical Society. Interviewed in Cleveland, OH
  - Eaton, Cyrus, 1973 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Estate employee at Forest Hill. Interviewed in Cleveland, OH
  - Goff, William S., 1973 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Son of JDR Sr's attorney in Standard Oil anti-trust suit. Interviewed in Cleveland, OH
  - Gogswell, Dewitt, 1973 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Son of Parma, Ohio school teacher who taught Franklin and William Rockefeller. Interviewed in Cleveland, OH
  - Haber, Kenneth, 1973 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Daughter of E. B. Rhodes. Interviewed in Cleveland, OH
  - Schneider, Hubert, 1973 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Lawyer with file on Frank Rockefeller. Interviewed in Cleveland, OH
  - Thompson, Josephine S., 1973 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Decendent of early friend of John D. Rockefeller, Sr. Interviewed in Cleveland, OH
  - Claude, Albert - Transcript, 1976 July 19-26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Cellular biologist at Rockefeller Institute, 1929-1949. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Pocantico Hills, NY
  - Claude, Albert - Transcript, 1976 July 19-26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Claude, Albert - Correspondence, Questions, Notes, First Draft of Transcript, 1976 July 19-26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Claude, Albert - Background and Research Materials, 1976 July 19-26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clear, Launcelot - Account, 1968 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Estate employee at Pocantico Hills, 1907-1961
  - Douglas, Howard - Account (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Messenger and receptionsit at the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller
  - Frasca, Leonard - Account, 1968 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Estate employee at Pocantico Hills. Interviewed in Pocantico Hills.
  - Hudson, James - Catalogue, Notes, 1973 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Associate of Winthrop Rockefeller. Interviewed by Linda Edgerly, New York, New York
  - Johnson, Walter - Account, 1968 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Estate employee at Pocantico Hills
  - Kimball, Lindsley F. - Transcript, 1980 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Rockefeller family associate. Interviewed by J. William Hess, Pocantico Hills, New York.
  - King, Charles S. - Catalogue, Handwritten, 1972 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Office Assistant at the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller, 1931-1972. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst.
  - Mambert, Helen, 1970 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rockefeller, Laura Chasin - Discussion with Abby Rockefeller Mauze - Notes, 1973 November 10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Daughter of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. Discussion with Laura Rockefeller Chasin, New York, New York.
  - McLeod, Mary - Catalogue, Notes, 1973 October 15 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Assistant to Winthrop Rockefeller, Executive Vice President and Treasurer of the RockWin Fund. Interviewed by Joseph W. Ernst, Little Rock, Arkansas.
  - Rockefeller, David - Transcript, 1975 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Interviewed by Richard Salomon, William Wing, Warren Lindquist and Joseph W. Ernst, Hudson Pines, New York
  - Rockefeller, David - Notes, Correspondence, Summaries of Conversations with David Rockefeller, Questions, Notes, 1975 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rockefeller, David - Notes, Background and Research Materials for Interview, 1975 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rockefeller, Jeannette - Transcript, Notes, 1974 April 22 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr. - Accounts, 1940; 1952-1955 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Interviewed by Raymond B. Fosdick
  - Walker, Robert B. - Account, 1968 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Pocantico Hills School Principal.
  - Wilson, Jack - Account (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Office Manager for General Education Board and Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller. Interviewed by Linda Edgerly, New York, New York
  - Wylock, Raymond - Account, 1968 April 18 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Willets, Edmund R. - Index (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Standard Oil Company representative in China. Accompanied John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to China in 1921.
  - Wirth, Conrad - Catalogue, Questions (Box 3, Folder 42)
    National Park Service Director and conservationist. Associate of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Laurance S. Rockefeller.
- Interviews and Oral History - Microfiche, 4
  - Albright, Horace M. - Transcript (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Conservationist (John D. Rockefeller, Jr.). From the Columbia University Oral History Collection.
  - Allen, William H. - Transcript, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Civic worker (Rockefeller Foundation, University of Chicago). From the Columbia University Oral History Collection.
  - Brophy, John - Transcript, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Labor Union official, United Mine Workers Union, Ludlow
  - Bruere, Henry - Transcript, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Civic worker, financier. Columbia Oral History Collection.
  - Delano, William A. - Transcript, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Architect, Kykuit. Columbia Oral History Collection.
  - Flexner - Abraham - Transcript, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Educator, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. Columbia Oral History Collection.
  - Hendrick, Burton J. - Transcript, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Writer, editor, magazine publisher (Ida Tarbell)
  - Sinclair, Upton - Transcript, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Author, muckraker. Columbia Oral History Collection.
  - Tweed, Harrison - Transcript, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Lawyer, New York City. Columbia Oral History Collection.
- Jackson Hole Preserve Project, 5
  - Burt, Mrs. Struthers and Nathaniel (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Chorley, Kenneth (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Fabian, Harold P. (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Hansen, Clifford (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Lawrence, W. C. (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Miller, Leslie A. (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Rockefeller, Laurance S. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Son of John D. Rockefeller, Jr and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
  - Wirth, Conrad (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Yokel, Michael (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Nelson A. Rockefeller Project, 6
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1977 December 12; 1978 February 2 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Robert Hartmann Interview with Nelson A. Rockefeller